Guide to the Oscar Wilde Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Oscar Wilde collection
1884-1915
GEN MSS 275
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Letters by Oscar Wilde to various parties, including Leonard Smithers and Frank Harris; letters between persons acquainted with Wilde, several manuscripts of writings by Wilde, including a notebook on Roman history, notes on travels in France and Spain, and "Phrases and Philosophies for the use of the young"; and several ephemeral items relating to Wilde.
Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900
Dreier, Katherine S. (Katherine Sophie), 1877-1952
Thomas, Abel Cary
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm is available for folder 24: Notebook containing notes on Roman history and draft of "Vera, or, the Nihilists." Consult Public Services staff.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Oscar Wilde, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into three series. The first series consists of items from the bequest of the estate of Katherine Dreier, principally letters removed from books (cataloged separately). The second series contains items given as a group by Abel Cary Thomas, mainly letters written by Wilde towards the end of his life. The third series, Additional Materials, contains two letters and several manuscripts, including notes by Wilde on his travels in France and Spain, and a draft of his "Phrases and Philosophies for the use of the young."
Authors, English -- 19th century; Harris, Frank, 1856-1931; Smithers, Leonard C. (Leonard Charles), 1861-1907; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900
- Materials given by Katherine Dreier, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Gift, 1954
  - Correspondence
    - Holland, Vyvian Beresford
      - 2 ALS to Thomas Werner Laurie, 1915 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Accompanied by photographs of Cyril Holland and Vyvian Holland; Removed from: Sherard, Robert Harborough. The Real Oscar Wilde, London 1916, Ip.w644.w916
    - Sherard, Robert Harborough
      - ALS to Thomas Werner Laurie, Norwood, 1914 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Removed from his: The Real Oscar Wilde, London, 1902, Ip.W644.W914
    - Smithers, Leonard Charles
      - TLS to Oscar Wilde, London, 1899 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Removed from: Sherard, Robert Harborough. Oscar Wilde, London, 1902, Ip.W644.W902S
    - Wilde, Jane Francesca (Elgee) Lady
      - ALS to Mrs. O'Connell, Chelsea, n.y. Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wilde, Oscar
      - ALS to Charles Godfrey Leland, New York, [1882] (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Accompanied by a typescript and a photograph of Wilde in 1878; bound in dark blue full morocco
      - ALS to Sir John Pentland Mahaffy, Chelsea (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - ALS to Robert Baldwin Ross, Paris, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 6 ALS and 4 telegrams (copies) to Leonard Smithers, London, 1897-99 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        The letters of 1897, Nov 16 and Dec 6 were removed from his: "The Ballad of Reading Gaol," 1899, Ip. W644.W898Bc.; The remaining letters and telegrams were removed from Sherard, Robert Harborough. Oscar Wilde, London, 1902, Ip.W644.W902S
  - Other Items
    - Extrait des minutes des actes de décès: a copy of the police department's official report of Oscar Wilde's death, Paris. Préfecture de la Seine., 1905 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Removed from: Sherard, Robert Harborough. Oscar Wilde, London, 1902 Ip.W644.S902S
    - Oscar Wilde's last hotel bill, made put to M. Melmouth, Hotel d'Alsace, Jean Dupoirier, Paris, 1900 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Materials given by Abel Cary Thomas, Series II
  Gift, 1931[?]
  - Correspondence
    - Wilde, Oscar
      - ALS to [Mrs. Bernard Beere] telling of his lodging place, and asking for news, Dieppe (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Signed with an assumed name, Sebastian Melmouth
      - ALS to Bernstein, asking him to bring three copies of the "Ballad" to be signed, Paris, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Typewritten copy laid in
        [02/14/2000: Letter appears to be a forgery]
      - ALS to Henry-D. Davray
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Box 1, folder 16
      - 3 ALS to Frank [Harris] the first and second thanking him for money and clothes, the third asking him for money with which to pay the hotel bill, Dieppe, Paris, [1900?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Accompanied by typewritten copies
      - ALS to Pierre Louÿs, in French, [London] (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Accompanied by typewritten copy
      - 4 ALS to his London publisher, Leonard Smithers, chiefly asking for money, [Paris?], [1899?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Typewritten copies of 3 letters laid in
        [02/14/2000: Last letter appears to be a forgery]
      - ALS to Henry-D. Davray expressing delight that his poem was to appear with Davray's translation [probably referring to the "Ballad of Reading Goal"], [Paris], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Accompanied by a typewritten copy
      - ALS to "Harold" acknowledging some communication and asking Harold to come that evening, Magdalen College, Oxford (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Writings
    - "Latin Verses:" holograph copy of four lines in Latin with the name "Oscar Wilde" at the end (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Accompanied by a typewritten copy of the verse, begins "Laurus cara mihi dando... "
    - "To my friend Luther Munday:" holograph copy signed by Oscar Wilde, 1891 Jan (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Published with title"Impression du matin" The World, 1881 Mar 2; reproduced in facsimile in the Picture Magazine, 1895 Feb 26, with the title, "To my friend Luther Munday"; Accompanied by a typewritten copy
  - Other Items
    - A photograph [Sarony], a reproduction of a photograph [J. Jacobs, London], and a reproduction of a drawing of Oscar Wilde [Mayer, Merkel, & Ottman, New York] (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Additional Materials, Series III
  - Correspondence
    - Wilde, Oscar
      - Typescript letter (transcript) to an unidentified recipient, Chelsea, S. W., [18]88 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Removed from: Wilde, Oscar, 1854- 1900. Happy prince and other tales by Oscar Wilde; illustrated by Walter Crane and Jacomb Hood, London: David Nutt; London and Edinburgh: Ballantyne Press; Ballantyne, Hanson and Co., 1888
        Gift, 1983
      - Bill, in French, from Auld Reekie, Scotch Tailors, Paris, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Gift, 1962
  - Writings
    - "The Ballad of Reading Gaol:" typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Accompanied with typed card, signed by Randolph H. Hill, describing this typescript as one of several copies made and "circulated privately in Springfield, Massacusetts, subsequent to its publication"; Published by Leonard Smithers, London, 1898; and B.R. Tucker, New York, 1899
      - Gift, 1951
    - [Notebook], holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Notes on Roman history: miscellaneous notes, possibly unpublished; "Vera, or, the Nihilists": early draft of the play privately printed in 1880; and 2 p. of aphorisms on love
      Gift, 1953
    - [Notes on travels in France and Spain], holograph (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Ex libris Richard Le Gallienne; laid in col: (1) transcript, typewritten of holograph; (2) 1 negative photostat of p. 2 of holograph
    - "O loved one lying far away:" holograph ms. poem, 6 stanzas, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Accompanied by TLS from Arthur Brentano and reproduction of sketch of Wilde, 1878
      Source unknown
    - Phrases and Philosophies for the use of the young: holograph, signed, Albemarle Club, London, [1894] (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Accompanied by: "The Chameleon", London: Gay and Bird, vol. 1, no. 1, 1894. No. 57 of an edition of 100 numbered copies. 1 vol. in a case
    - "Rose Leaves", holograph, signed, of poem, [1884] (Box 1, Folder 28)
      This poem, with revision and an extra stanza, was published under the title "Under the Balcony" in the Shakespearean Show Book, Manchester; accompanied by: typescript of a review published in Pall Mall Gazette, 1884 Jun 3